Danny Kaye and Sylvia Fine Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Danny Kaye and Sylvia Fine Collection 1893-1988 1924-1968
ML31.K397
Kaye, Danny
Fine, Sylvia
around 96,377 items 1,112 containers 435 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Danny Kaye (1913-1987) was an American actor, singer, dancer, comedian and humanitarian; his wife Sylvia Fine (1913-1991) was an American lyricist, composer, writer, lecturer and producer. The collection, which documents their lives and careers, contains printed and manuscript music, scripts, correspondence, business and financial papers, promotional and publicity materials, photographs, programs, posters, awards and realia.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Fine, Sylvia--Archives.; Fine, Sylvia--Correspondence.; Fine, Sylvia.; Fine, Sylvia.; Fine, Sylvia. Danny Kaye and Sylvia Fine collection. 1893-1988.; Fine, Sylvia. Selections.; Kaye, Danny--Archives.; Kaye, Danny--Correspondence.; Kaye, Danny--Photographs.; Kaye, Danny.; Kaye, Danny.
Organizations
Kaye (Danny)/Fine (Sylvia) Collection (Library of Congress) DLC
Subjects
Comedians--United States.; Entertainers--United States.; Motion picture music--Excerpts--Scores.; Music--Manuscripts.; Musical films--United States.; Musicals--Librettos.; Musicals--United States--Excerpts.; Musicals--United States.; Popular music--United States.; Television music--Excerpts--Scores.; Women composers--United States.; Women librettists--United States.
Titles
Danny Kaye show (Radio program); Danny Kaye show (Television program); Danny Kaye show (Television program); John Gary show.; John Gary show.; Musical comedy tonight II.; Musical comedy tonight II.; Musical comedy tonight III.; Musical comedy tonight III.; Musical comedy tonight.; Musical comedy tonight.
Form/Genre
Artifacts (Object genre); Awards.; Contracts.; Correspondence.; Financial records.; Photographic prints.; Posters.; Programs (Documents); Promotional materials.; Scrapbooks.; Scripts (Documents); Variety shows (Radio programs); Variety shows (Television programs)
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift; Sylvia Fine; 1990.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Transfers
Audiovisual materials have been transferred to the Library of Congress Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division. Some of the audiovisual materials have been cataloged separately and are identified as part of the "Kaye (Danny)/Fine (Sylvia) Collection (Library of Congress)."
Access and Restrictions
The Danny Kaye and Sylvia Fine Collection is open to research. The bulk of the collection is in off-site storage and researchers are advised to contact the Music Division prior to visiting in order to determine whether the desired materials will be available at that time.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1913, Jan. 18 David Daniel Kaminiski born, Brooklyn, New York First native-born American and youngest of three sons born to Clara and Jacob Kaminiski, both originally from the Ukraine
1913, Aug. 29 Sylvia Fine born, Brooklyn, New York One of three children born to Bessie and Dr. Samuel Fine, a dentist
1919 Fine began piano lessons
1923 Fine began studying harmony and musical theory Fine developed a fear of performing in front of large audiences; she became interested in writing and composing
circa 1925 Dr. Samuel Fine employed twelve-year-old David Daniel Kaminiski for a short period David and Sylvia met briefly
1928 Fine, an excellent student, graduated from Thomas Jefferson High School Fine enrolled in Hunter College (later known as Brooklyn College) to study music
1929 David took stage name of "Danny Kaye" Kaye began performing as a tummler at the White Roe Lake summer resort in the Catskill Mountains in New York. As such, he performed as a jester doing comedy, singing, and other entertainments between acts
1933 Kaye toured the Far East with dance group Three Terpischoreans Kaye began to craft his double-talk, babbling, and dialect routines Having no formal training as an actor, dancer, comedian, or singer, Kaye worked to enhance his natural abilities as a performer and entertainer
1937 Educational Pictures signed Kaye to appear in two-reel comedies Kaye appeared in three short films which were shown between features
1939 Kaye and Fine met again while working on a Max Liebman production that failed Liebman hired Fine to write specialty material for Tamiment, a summer camp in Pennsylvania Kaye was hired to work at Tamiment due to Fine's influence Fine wrote the Yiddish version of Gilbert and Sullivan's Mikado, "The Wolf of Wall Street," "Stanislavsky," and "Pavlowa," along with other material for Kaye, which were featured in Liebman's Broadway show, The Straw Hat Revue
1940, Jan. 13 Kaye and Fine married in a civil ceremony, Fort Lauderdale, Florida
1940, Feb. 22 Kaye and Fine married again in a formal wedding ceremony with family present
1940 Kaye performed Fine's material, including "Anatole of Paris," at Manhattan nightclub La Martinique
1941, Jan. 23 Kaye performed in Moss Hart's Lady in the Dark, in which he sang "Tschaikowsky," which was written by Ira Gershwin and Moss Hart
1941, Oct. 29 Kaye performed in Cole Porter's Let's Face It, in which he sang "A Melody in 4F" by Fine and Liebman
1943, Mar. 1 Fine helped negotiate a five-year movie contract for Kaye with Samuel Goldwyn
1943 Kaye legally changed his name to Danny Kaye
1944 Feb. Kaye starred in first feature film, Up in Arms, which included Fine and Liebman's "The Lobby Number" and "Melody in 4F"
1945 Kaye appeared in second feature film, Wonder Man, in which he exhibited his natural dance abilities while performing Fine's number "Bali Boogie"
1945-1946 CBS radio program The Danny Kaye Show aired (it was subtitled "Pabst Blue Ribbon Time")
1946, Dec. 17 Daughter Dena born (Kaye and Fine's only child)
1946 The Kid from Brooklyn was released; in the film, Kaye performed "Pavlowa" by Fine Kaye began performance tour in the United States between filming movies
1947 Kaye starred in The Secret Life of Walter Mitty which featured musical numbers by Fine, including "Anatole of Paris" and "A New Symphony for Unstrung Tongue" Kaye's first album released; it included "Deenah," "Minnie the Moocher," and Fine's "Anatole of Paris"
1948 A Song is Born featuring Kaye with Louis Armstrong, Benny Goodman, and Lionel Hampton was released; it was not considered a success at the box office and was the first film in which Kaye did not perform Fine's material Kaye toured Europe, to great acclaim
1949 Kaye starred in Inspector General, his first Warner Brothers film; Fine's contributions to the film included "The Gypsy Drinking Song" and "Soliloquy for Three Heads" After Inspector General flopped, the Kayes ended their contract with Warner Brothers and signed with 20th Century-Fox
1950 Kaye starred in On the Riviera, a 20th Century-Fox release, which included four songs by Fine; Gwen Verdon was featured as a lead dancer and served as assistant choreographer to Jack Cole
1952 Kaye starred in Hans Christian Andersen, a Goldwyn Studios production
1953 Kaye performed at the Palace Theatre on Broadway, to great acclaim
1954 Kaye named Ambassador-at-Large for the United Nations Children's Fund (UNICEF) Kaye's international visits with underprivileged children are documented in the UNICEF film Assignment: Children Kaye co-starred with Bing Crosby in White Christmas
1955 Kaye presented with special Academy Award for his humanitarian efforts
1956 Kaye performed Fine's material in the movie The Court Jester The Secret Life of Danny Kaye, a film documenting Kaye's work for UNICEF, aired on CBS
1957 Kaye starred in Merry Andrew
1958 Kaye's film Me and the Colonel was released by Columbia Pictures
1959 Kaye starred in The Five Pennies featuring music by Fine, including "Lullaby in Ragtime"
1960 Kaye performed at The Desert Inn in Las Vegas Kaye starred in and Fine produced his first television special, An Evening with Danny Kaye
1961 Kaye made On the Double Kaye starred in his second television special
1962 Kaye starred in The Man from the Diner's Club Kaye starred in his third television special
1963-1967 Kaye's weekly variety television series, The Danny Kaye Show, aired on CBS
1969 Kaye was featured in the film The Madwoman of Chaillot
1970 Kaye starred in the Richard Rodgers stage musical Two by Two
1971-1973 Kaye co-starred in the television musicals Peter Pan, Peter Cottontail, and Pinocchio Kaye embarked on a UNICEF tour of the United States Fine taught musical comedy, University of Southern California
1974 Kaye's Look-In at the Metropolitan Opera was televised and won an Emmy Award
1975 Fine began her lecture series on musical comedy at Yale University
1979 Fine's Musical Comedy Tonight, based on her lecture series, was broadcast on PBS
1981 Kaye appeared in Fine's Musical Comedy Tonight II Kaye starred in the television movie Skokie
1982 Kaye received the Jean Hersholt Humanitarian Award at the Academy Awards
1984 Kaye received the Kennedy Center Honor, along with Lena Horne, Isaac Stern, Gian Carlo Menotti, and Arthur Miller
1987, Mar. 2 Kaye died, Los Angeles, Calif.
1991, Oct. 29 Fine died, New York City
Scope and Content Note
The Danny Kaye and Sylvia Fine Collection documents the life and work of actor, singer, dancer and comedian Danny Kaye and his wife, lyricist, composer, writer, lecturer and producer Sylvia Fine. It includes printed and manuscript music, scripts, correspondence, business and financial papers, promotional and publicity materials, photographs, programs, posters, awards, and realia.
The Music series contains printed parts, scores, orchestral arrangements, and sheet music. Most of the music was used by Kaye for his television program The Danny Kaye Show (1963-1967), performance tours, movies, stage productions, and television specials. The series also includes compositions by Fine in the form of manuscripts, printed music, and lyric sheets, including "Anatole of Paris," "Life Could Not Better Be," and "Melody in 4F." In addition, there are other notable songs that Kaye performed, such as "Tschaikowsky," "The Dodgers Song," and "Ballin' the Jack." Music materials from The John Gary Show (1966), which was a summer replacement series for Kaye's television series The Danny Kaye Show, are in the collection as well.
The Scripts series includes scripts from Kaye's television series The Danny Kaye Show, which featured such guests as Lucille Ball, Gwen Verdon, Ella Fitzgerald, and Louis Armstrong. In addition, there are scripts from his radio series The Danny Kaye Show (1944-1946), The John Gary Show, and television specials such as Kaye's Look-In at the Metropolitan Opera (1974). The film scripts, some of which are housed in personalized leather binders and include black and white 8x10 photographs of movie scenes, include those for Up in Arms (1944), Hans Christian Andersen (1952), The Court Jester (1956), The Man from the Diner's Club (1962), and Skokie (1981).
The Correspondence series contains items to and from Kaye and Fine and is subdivided into Personal and Business subseries. Each subseries includes corespondence from individuals and organizations that reflect the various personal and professional interests of Kaye and Fine, including family, show business, politics, and social causes. Some correspondence contains additional printed material.
The Business Papers series contains materials related to Kaye's television program The Danny Kaye Show, The John Gary Show, films, tours, radio, recordings and special appearances. Materials include contracts, correspondence, financial reports, press and publicity materials, and production records.
The Musical Comedy Library series consists of materials related to a series of three television programs on musical theater that Fine produced and hosted: Musical Comedy Tonight (1979), Musical Comedy Tonight II (1981), and Musical Comedy Tonight III (1985). These shows were based on a series of lectures about musical comedy that Fine taught at the University of Southern California and Yale University. The music materials in the series include sheet music used in all three shows, arrangements from Kaye's television series The Danny Kaye Show and other Kaye performances, scores from various musicals, and miscellaneous printed sheet music. It also includes scripts for the three Musical Comedy Tonight shows, the The Danny Kaye Show, and The John Gary Show, and librettos from various musicals. In addition, the series contains books, photographs and slides, programs and press material, business papers, posters, production materials and set designs, research materials, scrapbooks, and sketches related to the production of the Musical Comedy Tonight series.
The Other series contains an array of materials, including awards; realia; scrapbooks; photographs; framed items, including caricatures, awards, and magazine covers; autographed books and magazines; and portrait paintings of Kaye. Many items in the series are accompanied by correspondence, programs, reviews and other printed material.
The awards include honorary degrees, certificates, citations, medals, plaques, statues, proclamations, and keys to cities. The list of awards is subdivided into those received by Kaye alone, by Fine alone, and by both. Danny Kaye received many awards for his humanitarianism, such as the Lions International Humanitarian Award (1973-1974), and several awards from the United Nations Children's Fund (UNICEF). The awards given to him as an entertainer include the Kennedy Center Honor (1984), induction into The Entertainment Hall of Fame Foundation (1974-1976), an Emmy Award (1963-1964), and several nominations from the National Academy of Television Arts and Sciences. Fine's awards include an Emmy Award (1975-1976) from the National Academy of Television Arts and Sciences, a George Foster Peabody Broadcasting Award (1979), and an award and appointment to the Advisory Committee on the Arts (1962) by John F. Kennedy.
The realia includes such items as an engraved walking stick from Harry Lauder (1949), a parachute, a bull whip, souvenir baseballs, statues, plaques, commemorative plates, paperweights, model airplanes, graduation robes, mementos, swords, trophies, and a variety of other items.
The audiovisual materials are housed in the Library of Congress Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division and are referenced in this finding aid by a catalog record number. These materials include videos of The Danny Kaye Show and recordings by Kaye.
Arrangement of the Danny Kaye and Sylvia Fine Collection
The Danny Kaye and Sylvia Fine Collection is arranged in six series:
Music
Scripts
Correspondence
Business Papers
Musical Comedy Library
Other
http://lccn.loc.gov/2006560770
Container List
- Music (Box 2-627, OV 868)
  - The Danny Kaye Show
    Parts (boxes 2-338) and score arrangements (boxes 550-626, OV 868) arranged chronologically by show number and alphabetically by title therein. If only parts are available or only full score arrangements are available, only the one respective box will be listed.
    - #1, LC Record #95-502768
      - Baseball man (Box 2, 550)
      - Bye bye blackbird (Box 2, 550)
      - Cherry pies (Box 2, 550)
      - Cleopatra's procession (Box 2, 550)
      - Elijah rock shout (Box 3, 550)
      - Film closing (Box 3, 550)
      - Film opening (Box 3, 550)
      - Front and center (Box 3, 550)
      - Life could not better be (Box 4, 550)
      - Love me Lady Powell (Box 4)
      - May there always be sunshine (Box 4)
      - My fair umpire (Box 4, 550)
      - Riverside (Box 5, 551)
      - Take me out to the ball game (Box 6, 551)
      - Walk around (Box 6, 551)
      - Walk it off (Box 6)
      - Walk right in (Box 7, 551)
      - West side story ball game (Box 7, 551)
    - #2, LC Record #95-503396
      - Brotherhood of man (Box 8, 552)
      - Celestial choir (Box 8, 552)
      - Film closing (Box 8)
      - Film opening (Box 8)
      - Forward in space (Box 8, 552)
      - Matador (Box 9, 552)
      - Relax with me (Box 9, 552)
      - Streets of Laredo (Box 9, 552)
      - Swingin' march dance (Box 9)
      - Telephone (Box 10, 552)
      - To be or not to be (Box 10, 552)
      - Three blind mice (Box 10, 552)
    - #3, LC Record #95-503412
      - Barrel of beauty (Box 11)
      - La belle of France (Box 11, 553)
      - Biltmore clock (Box 11, 553)
      - Clock song (I'm late) (Box 11, 553)
      - Fools rush in (Box 11, 553)
      - My grandfather's clock (Box 12, 553)
      - Old MacDonald (Box 12, 553)
      - Presentation time (Box 12, 553)
      - Rainy day (Box 13)
      - Rock around the clock (Box 13, 553)
      - Sonny's curls (Box 13, 553)
      - Wake up George (Box 13, 553)
      - Zip-a-dee-doo-dah (Box 553)
    - #4, LC Record #95-503449
      - Dancing pagodas (Box 14, 554)
      - Diner food (Box 14, 554)
      - Drum squad (Box 14, 554)
      - Lawrence ballet (Box 15)
      - Talent playhouse (Box 15, 554)
      - Talent playoff (Box 15, 554)
      - They call the wind Maria (Box 16, 554)
      - Together wherever we go (Box 16, 554)
      - Turn around (Box 16)
      - The victim (Box 16, 554)
    - #5, LC Record #95-503551
      - Ballin' the jack (Box 17, 555)
      - By myself (Box 17, 555)
      - Danny - Love Lady duet (Box 17, 555)
      - Days of wine & roses (Box 17, 555)
      - Friends of the family (Box 18, 555)
      - I could write a book (Box 18, 555)
      - It's so nice to have a man around the house (Box 18, 555)
      - Kaye/Kelly medley (Box 18, 555)
      - Madame's waltz (Box 19, 555)
      - Nola (Box 19, 555)
      - Side by side (Box 19, 555)
      - Varney's lunch (Box 19, 555)
      - You make me feel so young (Box 20, 555)
      - You'll never get away (Box 20, 555)
      - You're the cream in my coffee (Box 20, 555)
    - #6, LC Record #95-503706, #95-503715
      - Dee-lightful is the word (Box 21, 556)
      - Father knows nothing (Box 21, 556)
      - Father knows plenty (Box 21, 556)
      - A gypsy cries (Box 21)
      - Hard hearted Hannah (Box 21, 556)
      - I want a man (Box 22)
      - Jungle drums (Box 22, 556)
      - Mary Tyler Moore (Box 22, 556)
      - Osaka hillbillies (Box 23, 556)
      - Song & dance man (Box 23, 556)
      - Sposin' (Box 23, 556)
      - Vaude playoff (Box 23)
    - #7, LC Record #95-503717
      - Ashmolean (Box 24, 557)
      - Children's suite (Box 24, 557)
      - Drive in food (Box 25, 557)
      - I get so lonely (Box 25, 557)
      - Regal fanfare (Box 25, 557)
      - Song & dance playoff (Box 25, 557)
      - Two of a kind (Box 26, 557)
      - What is a woman (Box 26, 557)
    - #8, LC Record #95-503906
      - Arab finale (Box 27, 558)
      - Arabian evenings (Box 27, 558)
      - Commercial film #1 (Box 27)
      - Commercial film #2 (Box 27)
      - Get happy (Box 27, 558)
      - Gonna build a mountain (Box 28, 558)
      - Hospital bed (Box 28, 558)
      - It's de-lovely (Box 28, 558)
      - Michele (Box 29, 558)
      - Once in a lifetime (Box 29, 558)
      - Tea for two (Box 29)
      - We laugh (Box 29)
    - #9, LC Record #95-503909
      - Ach du lieber (Box 30, 559)
      - Dingle dangle school (Box 30)
      - Everybody out of the pool (Box 30, 559)
      - Fast drawers (Box 30, 559)
      - Hungarian rhapsody (Box 31, 559)
      - Inter-office exercise (Box 31, 559)
      - Kid's performance (Box 31, 559)
      - Lawrence of Arabia (Box 32, OV 868/1)
      - My father (Box 32, 559)
      - No manicure (Box 32, 559)
      - Record show (Box 32, 559)
      - She's a woody (Box 33, 559)
      - Stereo dance (Box 33, 559)
      - Sugartime (Box 33, 559)
      - Top hat (Box 33, 559)
    - #10, LC Record #95-503930
      - Angus McFangus (Box 34, 560)
      - Breezin' along with the breeze (Box 34, 560)
      - Come back again (Box 34, 560)
      - Igor Dingiling (Box 34, 560)
      - Johnny ding-a-lingo (Box 34, 560)
    - #11, LC Record #95-504257
      - Colonel Bogie (Box 35, 561)
      - Coronation fanfare (Box 35, 561)
      - Coronation march (Box 35, 561)
      - Fight (Box 35, 561)
      - Fight fight fight (Box 35, 561)
      - Happy hotel (Box 35, 561)
      - Indian sign (Box 36, 561)
      - Joannie Sommers (Box 36, 561)
      - King Louie's song (Box 36, 561)
      - Mozart musing (Box 36, 561)
      - Radio organ (Box 36)
      - Romeo and Juliet (Box 36, 561)
      - South rampart street parade (Box 37, 561)
      - The story of Alice (Box 38, 561)
    - #12, LC Record #95-504260
      - The barber of Seville (Box 39)
      - Bella Louie (Box 39)
      - Birth of the blues (Box 39, 562)
      - Dance of the hours (1 & 2) (Box 40, 562)
      - Danny boy (Box 40, 562)
      - Figaro (Box 41, 562)
      - Film closing (Box 41, 562)
      - Good morning (Box 41, 562)
      - Gypsy in my soul (Box 41, 562)
      - Rigoletto (Box 42, 562)
      - Surgery tonight (Box 42, 562)
      - Tarantella (Box 42, 562)
      - Toreador song (Box 42, 562)
      - Turkish harem (Box 42, 562)
      - Valkyries (Box 43, 562)
      - Walk right in (Box 43, 562)
    - #13, LC Record #95-504292
      - At last together (Box 44, 563)
      - The balcony song (Box 44)
      - Blossoms tag (Box 44)
      - Bow bells (Box 44, 563)
      - Closer walk (Box 44, 563)
      - Fair maiden I have traveled long (Box 44, 563)
      - Flower garden of my heart (Box 44)
      - Magnolia blossoms of 1932 (Box 45, 563)
      - Make believe (Box 45, 563)
      - Merrie England (Box 45, 563)
      - Open up your heart (Box 46, 563)
      - Professor Svengalsky (Box 46, 563)
      - Transatlantic ride (Box 46, 563)
      - When my sugar walks down the street (Box 46, 563)
    - #14, LC Record #95-504305
      - British train (Box 47, 564)
      - Bumble bee (Box 47, 564)
      - Dancing mood (Box 47, 564)
      - Hallelujah I love you (I love her so) (Box 48, 564)
      - Jingle bells on and off (Box 48, 564)
      - Timptation (Box 48, 564)
      - Tomorrow mountain (Box 564)
      - Yesterdays (Box 564)
    - #15, LC Record #95-504328
      - French medal (Box 49, 565)
      - Simon says (Box 49, 565)
      - Swingin' the news (Box 50, 565)
      - That great come and get it day (Box 50, 565)
      - Truly Julie Newmar (Box 50, 565)
      - Wa wa (Box 50, 565)
      - Yo ho (Box 50, 565)
    - #16, LC Record #95-504337
      - Christmas gifts (Box 51, 566)
      - Courtroom capers (Box 51, 566)
      - Happy wedding (Box 51, 566)
      - Hello ladies (Box 51, 566)
      - Puttin' on the ritz (Box 52, 566)
      - Santa's call (Box 52, 566)
      - Spy dance (Box 52)
      - Verdict blues (Box 52, 566)
      - Xmas season (Box 53, 566)
      - You meet the nicest people (Box 53, 566)
    - #17, LC Record #95-504339
      - Baby it's cold outside (Box 54, 567)
      - Comes once in a lifetime (Box 54, 567)
      - Dancing styles (Box 54)
      - In Vienna (Box 55, 567)
      - Jingle journey (Box 55, 56, 567)
      - Old King Cole (Box 57, 567)
      - That's how I feel (Box 57, 567)
      - Vienna reprise (Box 57, 567)
    - #18, LC Record #95-504343
      - Big Louie (Box 58, 568)
      - Check for two (Box 58)
      - Gangster hideout (Box 58)
      - I'm five (Box 568)
      - John Henry (Box 58, 568)
      - Lazy river (Box 58, 568)
      - My love is a wanderer (Box 59, 568)
      - New baby (Box 568)
      - Prison camp (Box 59, 568)
      - Ship waiter (Box 59, 568)
      - Tea (Box 59, 568)
      - Tea for two (Box 59, 568)
      - Tea is land (Box 59, 568)
      - Tico tico (Box 60, 568)
      - Vienna (Box 60, 568)
      - We belong together (Box 60, 568)